<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Buddha.Bike</title>
    <description>If you limit your activity to what you can do just now, in this moment, then you can express fully your true nature, which is the universal Buddha nature. When you bow, you should just bow; when you sit, you should just sit; when you eat, you should just eat; [when you ride, you should just ride]. - Shunryu Suzuki</description>
    <link>http://buddha.bike/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://buddha.bike/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 14:00:28 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2019 14:00:28 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fat Pursuit!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick note to give the tracking links for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://fatpursuit.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fat Pursuit&lt;/a&gt; ride. Trackleaders is monitoring the race &lt;a href=&quot;http://trackleaders.com/fatpursuit19&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; And my personal track is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race is a lot like the Susitna 100 I did last year (see my &lt;i&gt;Rolling on the River&lt;/i&gt; post) but about 15 miles longer and has quite a bit more elevation change. The Fat Pursuit takes place in the “Yellowstone ecosystem” right on the border of Idaho and Wyoming, so it’s bound to be beautiful. Looking forward to this adventure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 8 p.m.&lt;/strong&gt; - Dad and I just returned from the pre-race meeting and dinner. It was encouraging and inspring to meet the fellow riders–adventurous spirits all. Jay and Tracy Petervery are fine hosts, and you can tell this is a labor of love for them. It’s an honor to be among this crew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 10 a.m., 1/6&lt;/strong&gt; - An incredible ride! Although a significant snow dump beginning around 10 last night prevented me from completing the ride, I feel like I gave this one my all and am satisfied with the outcome. I bivvied out from 2 to 5 this morning and hiked back to the West Yellowstone checkpoint (a feat in and of itself) to find my dad ready with the car. Always grateful for the support crew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=1c39b5c25515af0e51&amp;amp;hoursPast=0&amp;amp;showAll=yes&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=1c39b5c25515af0e51&amp;amp;hoursPast=0&amp;amp;showAll=yes&quot;&gt;See full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 05:30:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/routes/2019/01/04/fatpursuit-note.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/routes/2019/01/04/fatpursuit-note.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>routes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Follow my &quot;Spot Dot&quot; on the Arizona Trail</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, September 22 I’ll embark on a bikepacking tour of the Arizona Trail. That morning, the map below ought to begin to track my progress every five minutes. It’s always energizing (and a comfort) to know that I’ll have some friends along for the ride – albeit via satellite. For more detail about the terrain I’ll be traveling, and my likely stops along the way, download a &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/arizona_trail_map.pdf&quot; download=&quot;Arizona Trail Map&quot;&gt;map of my route&lt;/a&gt; and the corresponding &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/AZT_Elevation_Chart.pdf&quot; download=&quot;Arizona Trail Map&quot;&gt;elevation relief&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 9/24&lt;/strong&gt; - Alas, it seems a thru-bike of the AZT wasn’t meant to be. After two days mostly hike-a-biking the fifty miles from the Mexico/US border to Patagonia I decided to come on home (I’m in the car now, nearing the TX/AR line). My mother, who dropped me off at the trailhead on Sunday was still in the area and was able to pick me up in Patagonia. Thanks Mom! The scenery was gorgeous – I found one of the greatest campsites of all time – and yet the midday heat and the extreme exertion involved in pushing a seventy pound bike up the loose, rocky hills cancelled out the fun factor fast, and I’m pretty sure I was close to heat exhaustion. It was a tough decision to call it, but also an easy one once I realized what would be safest. Although the experience was shorter than planned, there’s still a good story in it – I just need some time to sort it all out in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=1afea5b8c699b7e2bc&amp;amp;hoursPast=0&amp;amp;showAll=yes&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=1afea5b8c699b7e2bc&amp;amp;hoursPast=0&amp;amp;showAll=yes&quot;&gt;See full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 12:28:53 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/routes/2018/09/16/azt-track.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/routes/2018/09/16/azt-track.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>routes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Packing for the Arizona Trail</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing out the details of my bikepacking gear is just as much an exercise in thoroughness as it is an opportunity to share knowledge. Plus, I’ve always wanted to take one of those pre-bikepacking, OCD-esque gear layout photos. Readers, don’t hesitate to shoot me an email if you see that I’m missing something!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 100%; height: auto; &quot; src=&quot;/assets/azt_gear.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bike&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; For transportation along the AZT I’ll be peddling  my trusty steel Surly Krampus. It’s a fully rigid mountain bike with “plus size” 29” wheels. The rims are 45mm WTB Scrapers mounted tubeless with 3” WTB Ranger tires – built ‘em up myself. The 1x drivetrain is geared with a 11/42 cassette and a 28T chainring. I have great confidence in this bike’s ability to endure the rugged AZT terrain, however, its heartiness comes at a price – its heavy. Hopefully that 28T chainring will make up the difference. Oh yeah, it’s red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bags&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I have a full set of well-loved Revelate Designs bags that performed flawlessly on the Tour Divide. They’ll keep me company again on the AZT. The harness and pocket will carry my sleeping pad, sleeping bag, tent poles, and other quick-access gear. The frame bag will hold my bike repair kit, first aid kit, bathroom kit, and pump. The gas tank will hold snacks. The mountain feed bags will carry water bottles. I’ll load up my nano panniers with food and electronics, draped over my Old Man Mountain rear rack. On top of the rack I’ll have a lightweight Seal Line dry bag containing my tent, extra cloths, cook set and stove, all strapped down with two Surly Junk Straps. In a Salsa Anything Cage on the fork I’ll strap an Anything Bag stuffed with my rain gear and wool jersey. And finally, I’ll wear a JanSport fanny pack for my GoPro, phone, glasses, and sunscreen (Yes, the family is having lots of fun ribbing me about the fanny pack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sleep System and Shelter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I’m going vintage on the sleeping bag this time around and digging out my purple, synthetic North Face 30 degree bag. I used it on the AT a bunch of years ago so it’s probably no longer good down to 30 degrees, but it’s pretty light and very compressible. It also comes loaded with a nasty smell – something you can’t buy from REI. My Ridgerest pad is also from my AT days, but I’ve chopped it down to 3/4 length. It will double as something to sit on while I’m cooking. And my shelter is a solo Big Agnes Fly Creek UL tent. It was bomb proof on the Tour Divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Water and Filtration&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Getting the water system right is paramount on the AZT. I’ve opted to go with water bottles, as I’ve never warmed to bladders and hoses. I’ll have four bottles strapped to my bike (one on the underside of the downtube, one on my fork, and two in my mountain feed bags). That gives me almost three liters. I’ll also carry a two-liter Platypus bladder in reserve. This system worked well on the Tour Divide, but I’m anticipating needing to fill the Platypus more than I did then – it just means extra weight. For filtration, I’m trying out the MSR Trailshot. It’s just “so hot right now” in the bikepacking crowd that I couldn’t pass it up. This is a switch from my Polar Pure iodine mixture, but I understand AZT water primarily comes in the form of mud pools and cow troughs, so, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clothing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I will have two lightweight Smartwool t-shirts, two pairs of Pearl Izumi bike shorts, two pairs of wool socks, one pair of Patagonia capeline boxers (for sleeping), one pair of cool weather bike pants, one long sleeve Ibex wool jersey, two pairs of bike gloves, one bike cap, one bike helmet, and one pair of prescription sunglasses. My rain gear will consist of a pair of lightweight GoreTex Patagonia pants and a lightweight Marmot Jacket. My shoes are Shimano XM7’s – also all the rage with the bikepacking crowd these days. They’re rugged and flexible enough to serve as my Grand Canyon hiking shoes as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Electronics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Honestly, dealing with electronics in the wilderness is kind of a pain. Back on the AT I had a cell phone but hardly ever any service. My parents and I had a scheduled Thursday evening phone call each week, if I recall, and all I had to do was give the phone a charge at a restaurant here and there and everything would work. My camera was a Kodak with regular film and I’d just mail home the exposed rolls. Today, on the other hand, some serious thought has to go into these things! I’ll bring my iPhone which I will use for calls, texts and the occasional photo. My GoPro (with mini tripod) will serve as my primary video and still camera (three SD cards and three rechargeable batteries in tow). My bike headlight, &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/2016/04/29/idling-with-phil.html&quot;&gt;a Scalfano special&lt;/a&gt;, is accompanied by two lithium ion batteries and a charger. My Garmin eTrex 30x needs spare lithium AA’s and my Spot Tracker needs spare AAA’s – and I’ll be carrying several of each. Finally, I will bring an Anker PowerCore 20100 which will serve as my on-the-trail charger for everything. It’s fairly high capacity (and therefore heavy) and so I’ll likely have to charge it just a couple times during the trip. Unlike my ride on the Tour Divide, I will not be using a generator hub. I anticipate slow, uneven speeds on the AZT, which makes a generator hub fairly inefficient. Plus, I didn’t want to drop another $200 on a boost-size generator hub!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cooking and Food&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; My cook set, also a repeat traveler from the Tour Divide, is a GSI Soloist, and my stove is an MSR Pocket Rocket. I have a purple titanium spork as well. I plan to fire up the stove for breakfast and dinner, as I’ve always enjoyed taking the time to cook meals when I can. It’s a reminder to slow down and take things in. Breakfast staples will be rolled oats, brown sugar, walnuts, and coffee (Starbucks Vias). Dinners will generally consist of pasta, tuna, mac and cheese, and other quick prep meals with high calorie counts. I’ll be snacking throughout the day on various energy bars and goo shots, salty chips, and candy. I plan on supplementing my trail food with the occasional restaurant stop whenever I go through town. As always, I’ll be on the lookout for the ubiquitous gas station fried pie. At 1500 calories per pie, those things are bikepacking gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bike Repair Kit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Aside from the standard two tubes, pre-glued patches, chain scrubber (toothbrush), chain lube, zip-ties, multi-tool, rag, spare cleat/bolts, and quick links, I always bring along a set of quick link pliers as well – a little heavy for the road, but always come in handy when you have a chain problem. #beenthere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;First Aid&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Well, I’m still a certified NOLS Wilderness First Responder, so I’ll take my brain with me – and maybe my certificate to inspire some confidence. (o: Aside from that, I have some band-aids, gauze, moleskin, Neosporin, a bunch of ibuprofen, and some athletic tape. I’m counting on my knees acting up around day three, so I’ll need to get tape underneath my kneecap and work out that IT band. My Spot Tracker SOS button is always with me as well, albeit a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bathroom Kit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; TP, hand sanitizer, chamois cream, Dr. Bronner’s (for washing clothes and dishes), and a stylish orange titanium cat hole shovel. ‘Nuff said.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 12:26:53 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/gear/2018/09/15/azt-gear.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/gear/2018/09/15/azt-gear.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gazing at the Moon from the Arizona Trail</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m currently wrapping up a read of Tom Wolfe’s &lt;em&gt;The Right Stuff&lt;/em&gt;, a poetic chronicle of the Mercury Seven astronauts. If you haven’t read the book you’ve probably seen the 1983 movie of the same name. Who can forget Ed Harris’s portrayal of John Glenn, the “Boy Scout” astronaut and first American to orbit the planet? How about Sam Shepard’s swaggering Chuck Yeager, the first man to scream through the upper atmosphere and break the sound barrier (while recovering from a couple of broken ribs and nursing a hangover from the night before no less)? The right stuff, writes Tom Wolfe, is something “a man either had or didn’t! There was no such thing as having most of it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two and many others involved in the early days of NASA are lauded by our nation as some of the most adventurous individuals to ever live, risking their lives for a greater cause. It’s likely that the national focus on a “greater cause” is what actually gave rise to this age of national heroes. Beyond simply beating the Soviets into space, we wanted to test the limits of humanity – scientific, intellectual, creative, emotional, and physical. Collectively, we wanted to see if we could turn our wildest dreams into reality. And so we strapped those who had the “right stuff” to the top of roman candles, lit the fuses, and held our breath. We were bold and courageous, and the payoff was no less than a “giant leap for mankind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1960’s was a golden age of big ideas, and that same larger-than-life energy that fueled the space race was also at work in the minds of others. With the sky no longer the limit, literally, it seemed that anything was possible. In 1968, caught up in the electrifying spirit of an impending moon landing, Congress joined together to pen some large-scale, gutsy bills a little closer to home. In October of that year it passed the National Trails System Act “to promote the preservation of, public access to, travel within, and enjoyment and appreciation of the open-air, outdoor areas and historic resources of the Nation.” The act immediately named the 2100-mile Appalachian Trail and the 2600-mile Pacific Crest Trail as National Scenic Trails, offering them protection and maintenance akin to that the National Parks enjoy. Since the act was passed, over 50,000 miles of trail have been added to the national system. And, in the spirt of the age of their inception, they encourage patrons to hike a little farther, to climb a little higher, and to dream a little bigger than they thought they could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, there is a little bit of the moon in these trails, I think. To journey along one is to join with other daring souls in that unique American desire to test limits and break barriers. The National Trails allow everyone the opportunity to discover the “right stuff” within themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I doubt I will walk on the moon anytime soon, I might as well get as close as I can by gazing at it on a clear desert night from the Arizona Trail, one of America’s eleven National Scenic Trails. It’s been seventeen years since I completed an end-to-end journey on one of its oldest cousins, the Appalachian Trail, and I have been feeling the need to return. This time, though, I’ll be riding my bike instead of hiking (easier on the knees), I’ll be out for two and a half weeks instead of five and a half months (easier on the job and family), and I’ll be in my forties instead of my twenties (easier to find my way home at the end). No, I’m not looking to risk my life for a greater cause like those early astronauts – the rescue team is only as far away as the button on my Spot Track device – but I am hoping to glimpse a bit of the view that John Glenn had from his small capsule window, a view that might gain me some perspective. How can one not be changed by seeing the swirling, blue-green Earth zip underneath while in rapid orbit around it? How can one not be moved by the grand scope of it all? I realize  I won’t be speeding in a spaceship at 17,000 miles-per-hour, but rather chugging along on a bike averaging somewhere around 7. I do hear, though, that the desert, like outer space, has been known to bring a kind of revelation all its own to those who make the journey. I’m counting on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A little more about the journey.&lt;/strong&gt; Unlike the AT, the AZT permits mountain bikes – but that doesn’t mean it’s all rideable. I’ve been told the trail offers some of the best mountain biking there is – and plenty of equally impressive “hike-a-bike” to keep the ego in check. In fact, through the Grand Canyon, hikers are asked to either strap their bike to their back and hike the nineteen miles down and up or shuttle it around the canyon via local motorized transport!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://aztrail.org/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Arizona Trail&lt;/a&gt; spans the entire state, from its southern border with Mexico to its northern border with Utah. For hikers, the trail distance spans just over 800 miles. Bikers get a bit of a break at 750 miles due to reroutes around National Wilderness areas, which don’t allow bikes. There are a number of bikers who have carved out the trail in recent years, some soloists like myself, and others as participants in the annual race, which usually takes place in April. Much like the Tour Divide from Canada to Mexico, the AZT race asks that competitors ride self-supported, carrying all their gear and food, resupplying along the way or via prearranged maildrop, and that they stick to a generally accepted route, of which there are several. Although I won’t be racing with the pack, I plan to follow the rules with one exception. After some serious soul searching, I’ve decided to have my bike shlepped around the Grand Canyon instead of packing it down myself. I’ve disassembled and hoisted the steel Surly beast and all it’s gear onto my back several times and no matter how much I balance and re-balance the weight, 70 lbs is 70 lbs. Of course, I’m still planning to hike through the canyon and camp at one of its historic campgrounds (if I can secure a walk-up backcountry permit, which is apparently something the National Park Service offers to thru-hikers/bikers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the rugged terrain, and water being somewhat scarce due to the desert climate, enduring the heat can also be a challenge. I will begin my ride on September 22, the beginning of one of two acceptable seasons for a thru-bike (the other being April), however, despite it officially being fall at that point, the weather gods in Arizona won’t necessarily follow suit. It’s predicted to be in the 90’s during my traverse of the Tucson/Phoenix region, but it will most certainly get cooler the farther north I go as the elevation increases. Here’s to sunscreen and a high carrying capacity for water! If all goes as planned, the entire trip should take me seventeen days. That’s approximately fifty miles each day with the exception of the two  &lt;em&gt;leisurely&lt;/em&gt; ten-mile days I will be in the Grand Canyon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download a &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/arizona_trail_map.pdf&quot; download=&quot;Arizona Trail Map&quot;&gt;map of my route&lt;/a&gt; and the corresponding &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/AZT_Elevation_Chart.pdf&quot; download=&quot;Arizona Trail Map&quot;&gt;elevation relief&lt;/a&gt;, or play with the interactive map below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/arizona-trail_223114?scaleControl=false&amp;amp;miniMap=false&amp;amp;scrollWheelZoom=false&amp;amp;zoomControl=true&amp;amp;allowEdit=false&amp;amp;moreControl=true&amp;amp;searchControl=null&amp;amp;tilelayersControl=null&amp;amp;embedControl=null&amp;amp;datalayersControl=true&amp;amp;onLoadPanel=undefined&amp;amp;captionBar=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/arizona-trail_223114&quot;&gt;See full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 12:26:53 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/routes/2018/09/14/azt-moon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/routes/2018/09/14/azt-moon.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>routes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tour Divide Journal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had originally intended to transcribe my Tour Divide journal entries onto the web, editing along the way, but I thought it might be a little more authentic to put them up “as is.” My handwriting is mostly legible – to me, at least. It has been fun to read through the experience and remember just how challenging, inspring, and transformative it was. Keep on truckin’!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/adventures/2015/09/28/my-people.html&quot;&gt;Discovering My People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/adventures/2015/09/29/tupac-in-banff.html&quot;&gt;Tupac in Banff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/adventures/2015/09/30/jayps-good-advice.html&quot;&gt;JayP's Good Advice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The above posts are my first three Tour Divide journal entries, transcribed and reworked. The handwritten entries below begin where the posts leave off.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june14.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june15.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june16.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june17.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june17-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june18.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june18-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june19.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june19-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june20.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june20-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june21.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june21-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june22.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june23.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june24.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june24-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june25.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june25-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june26.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june26-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june27.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june27-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june28.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june28-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june29.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/june30.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july1-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/adventures/2015/10/22/why-afraid.html&quot;&gt;Why are you afraid?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;I reworked the July 1 entry into a piece that was published in The Cordillera, an annual anthology of Tour Divide tales.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july2-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july3-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july4-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july5-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july5-3.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july6-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july7.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/july7-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 13:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/04/18/divide-journal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/04/18/divide-journal.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>adventures</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rolling on the River</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 175px; height: auto; &quot; src=&quot;/assets/susitna-drawing.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; hspace=&quot;10px&quot; /&gt;The last time I saw Matt Beedle was a dozen years ago at his wedding. I was a newlywed myself and Kate was pregnant with Luke at the time. My third year of seminary was about to start and, as such, Matt and Amy figured I had been trained up enough to preach the homily. If I recall, the Gospel that day was the story of the transfiguration on the mountaintop – a fitting  theme for our relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt and I grew up in Juneau, Alaska climbing mountains together. Thunder, Juneau, McGinnis, Jumbo, Roberts, Nugget, Cairn, Observation – you name it, we climbed it, enjoying the mountaintop experience each time. And now, after more than a decade of climbing up metaphorical mountains in the other parts of our lives, we reconnected back in Alaska to take on another one together. In two days we would participate in the Susitna 100 – not a literal mountain, but a climb nonetheless. The Susitna 100 is a 100 mile loop through the Alaskan wilderness, which winds its way through the woods, across frozen lakes, and along the ice-covered Susitna River. Part of the route follows the Iditarod trail on which the famed sled-dog race takes place each year. Alongside about a hundred others, we would ride our fatbikes, fully loaded with survival gear, through the Alaskan winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to see Matt again. And it didn’t take long for the familiar excitement of an adventure together to make that decade apart feel like nothing. We knew each other the way only childhood friends could, having shared countless formative experiences. It’s a rare and valuable thing to be known that way. We caught up over Alaskan Amber and pizza at the Moose’s Tooth in Anchorage. Conversation flowed effortlessly from work and family joys and concerns to goofy banter about cycling gear and the unfamiliar challenges of riding in the snow. It was good to have a companion on this crazy adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it really was a crazy adventure. Throughout my bikepacking career I had often come across tales of cyclists participating in Alaska rides like the Susitna 100, and I had considered these events to be the ultimate challenge both mentally and physically, the pinnacle ride being the Iditarod Trail Invitational, a 1000 mile journey along the entire Iditarod route from Anchorage to Nome. Rides like JayP’s Fat Pursuit, the Arrowhead 135, and the Susitna 100 are qualifiers for the ITI. One had to finish three such events to be invited to participate in the ITI 350 – covering the Iditarod route from Anchorage to McGrath – which, after successful completion, would allow one to return for the full 1000 mile event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, back in the summer of 2017 I decided to sign up for the Susitna 100 – I had to see if this winter fatbiking thing lived up to its wild reputation. I cajoled Matt in to joining me and we began to assemble all of the necessary equipment and plot out our training schedules, him on the snow covered trails of eastern British Columbia and me on the dirt roads Arkansas. Caught up in the excitement of it all, I got a wild hair and emailed the ITI organizer to see about getting into the 350 based on my existing riding credentials. The ITI was just a week after the Susitna 100 and since I would already be in Alaska for that event why not stick around and go for the big one? To my surprise and delight she accepted my application but gave me a spot on the wait list since the roster had already filled. I would learn if I would move to the active roster sometime after the new year. Either way, I was headed to Alaska, and I was thrilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alaska and Arkansas both hold the title “home” for me. My family is originally from Arkansas. I was born in Hot Springs, went to college in Conway, and have traveled the state extensively over the past decade as priest serving the Episcopal Church. My love for cycling was also born here and has been deeply formed by the Ouachita mountains and the friends who have ridden through them with me. Alaska, though, like my friend Matt, seems to know me uniquely. The people there saw me through all the successes and failures of my youth and claimed me after returning from my journey down the Appalachian Trail while I fumbled through life’s next steps. Alaska has known me as me. So, taking my bicycle up to the Last Frontier meant more than simply entering another race. It would be a homecoming of sorts, and a melding of two great loves. I was beyond excited to make the introduction: cycling and Alaska – fatbike and snow. How would the two get along?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the big date approached – just two weeks out from the Susitna 100 and three from the ITI – an email from the ITI organizer landed in my inbox inviting me to fill a vacated spot on the roster. The timing was a little tight, but how could I say no? I asked Kate to join me for lunch at our local noodle bar so I could share the news. And over some pan fried dumplings, she gave me her blessing. She and the kids would get into their routine, she assured me. They had done it before, following my SPOT tracker dot online each day – digitally connecting through the miracle of GPS satellites. From past experience, I knew I would miss them more than I could feel at that moment. I changed my plane tickets, sent off my registration fee, and started to mentally prepare. The Susitna 100 was just a century, right? I had done lots of centuries before. It would be a perfect warmup for the more challenging ITI a week later. I had this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day before the race Matt and I took our fully-loaded bikes on a test ride on a trail just outside of Anchorage. We had a stellar view of Denali in the distance and of a moose just 50 yards away. My bike and Alaska seemed to be getting along just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Susitna 100 started at Happy Trails Kennel, the home base of four-time Iditarod sled-dog race champion, Martin Buser. Martin has been a dedicated supporter of the Susitna 100 over the years, and an inspiration to all of the riders, runners, and skiers bold enough to roll up to the starting line. As Matt and I drove up in the wee hours of race day, the dogs were up and yelping, as if to welcome the intrepid cyclists onto their historic trail. Like any other race I had been to, the parking lot was full of nervous racers, absorbed in their thoughts, pumping up tires and making sure all the necessary gear was accounted for – the only difference was that the temperature was -8 degrees Fahrenheit. I made the mistake of touching my steel fork with a bare hand while strapping on a bag and felt an instant burn. This was surreal. After a last minute hot water top-up for my water bottles, Matt and I rolled into the crowd at the starting line and the gun went off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I would come to learn, the extreme temperatures are a major factor on these rides. That sounds like a obvious statement, I know, but the &lt;i&gt;idea&lt;/i&gt; of -8 degrees and the &lt;i&gt;reality&lt;/i&gt; of -8 degrees are vastly different. The disconnect is akin to packing food for a bikepacking trip on a full stomach – you tend to underestimate how hungry you think you’ll be out there and you often pack less than you need to. For me, the unanticipated reality of riding in the cold was that it is inescapable. When you are riding you can’t wear your heaviest clothing or you will sweat too much, and if you stop for awhile you will get cold – unless you take the time to put on your heavy coat – but then you’re not moving, which means you will spend more time out in the cold! The trick to keeping hypothermia at bay is to find equilibrium among pace, layering, and temperature. And at around mile five I feel like I had gotten a feel for it, save for the fact that my pace seemed significantly slower than that of the other racers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt and I had a talked about allowing each other the freedom to go at our desired paces – everyone’s equilibrium is a little different – and he shot out at the start fairly quickly. I took it easy in order to get my bearings, as I tend to do at race starts. After an hour or so, though, I just felt sluggish. My “always go pace” wasn’t as quick as it should be, and I could no longer see any other riders behind me (“Always go pace,” by the way, is the pace at which I feel I can maintain, or “always go” regardless of how long I’m peddling. It tends to correlate more with heart rate zone than actual speed, I think. I know it when I’m in it.). And so, just five miles into the Susitna 100 the self-talk began. I thought I would at least have gotten a few more miles behind me before I had to start reciting internal mantras: &lt;i&gt;Ride your own ride. One pedal stroke at a time. Keep on truckin’.&lt;/i&gt; These magic little phrases wouldn’t make me go any faster but they would, hopefully, keep my head in the game. And then out of nowhere I got passed … &lt;i&gt;by a runner&lt;/i&gt; dragging his sled full of survival gear! I couldn’t quite believe it. What was going on? I hadn’t stopped anywhere. Was I really just this slow? Had all those hard miles I had put in back at Lake Sylvia in Arkansas really earned me no more than the back of the pack up here in Alaska? It just didn’t add up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next 20 miles were rough to say the least. The mantras weren’t quite cutting it, although I did manage to pass a few riders, which gave me a boost. A couple poor guys were trying to troubleshoot mechanical issues and another couple were struggling to haul their bikes up a steep icy slope – I wasn’t the only one fighting the fight. I played a game of leapfrog with my runner friend for awhile, which was a pleasant, but incredibly humbling diversion. That guy was a beast. He got to know me by my bib number and we would encourage each other whenever one of us passed (I scored the memorable bib #1 by virtue of having Alexander as a last name.). But I just couldn’t manage to shake this heavy feeling of dread. I wasn’t necessarily having “fun” per se and calculating a finish time based on my current speed was just depressing. The painful truth I could no longer keep out of my mind was that the ITI was simply out of reach for me. I’ve always been wary of making big decisions during difficult moments, but somehow this was different. It was more fear than exhaustion, I think, more of a growing understanding that failure out here had real consequences. I just didn’t want to get in over my head, and realizing that the ITI was over my head hit me pretty hard – a crippling blow to the ego.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one overwhelming moment around mile 25 the weight of it all just took me down. I stopped right in the middle of the trail, bowed my head over my handlebars, and cried like I hadn’t cried in a long time. &lt;i&gt;Would my tears freeze too?&lt;/i&gt; I had dreamed about the ITI for years and had been planning for months. I had been granted a spot on the roster, the event was just one week away, and the drop bags I had prepared were probably already on their way up to the Finger Lake and Rohn checkpoints. The ITI was to be my “next thing,” the event I had graduated to after having completed the Tour Divide – I was &lt;i&gt;supposed&lt;/i&gt; to do it. And yet, winter fatbiking was slower, colder, and more mentally exhausting than I could have imagined. I couldn’t fathom setting up a bivouac in these temperatures, dealing with frozen gear and food, and giving it my all just to barely maintain a four mile per hour pace. This was &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; how this was supposed to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outburst surprised me, but I found myself grateful for it – my body taking control for a moment to let my mind know that it needed to slow down and begin to triage my thoughts. I looked up. The sun was out, the sky was bright blue, the landscape was breathtaking. The storm was in my mind. I realized that I had to let go of the ITI and concentrate on the Susitna 100. I was just a quarter of the way through my current ride, and if I didn’t put my attention where it needed to be, right here and now, I risked the possibility of losing both rides. Every thought about the ITI was draining precious mental energy away from my current predicament, and I didn’t have an ounce to spare. I had to let it all go – not just the ITI but also frustration with being at the back of the pack, depression about pace calculations, and the ego slap of being passed by that machine of a runner! I had to be here now. And so that became my new mantra: &lt;i&gt;Be here now. Be here now. Be here now.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next 40 miles were much better. The terrain didn’t change – in fact, the snow softened up a bit around midday and I was forced to get off and push for a few miles. The temperature didn’t change all that much either. It was still cold. And I can’t say that I ever really picked up the pace. The change, though, was in my head. The raging storm inside calmed down enough for me to began to see things a little more clearly. In fact, I got a cathartic laugh in at one point!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that crashing is a fairly common occurrence while winter fatbiking. “Crashing” may actually be too strong of a word to describe the phenomenon. It’s really more like gently falling into a soft, cold pillow. I know from experience. Occasionally you’ll run over an unexpected soft spot and lose your balance, or you’ll drift too far to the side of the trail, get sucked into the berm, and ignominiously bite it. It’s never graceful! Although I was alone for much of the ride, I felt the presence of kindred sprits throughout – often witnessing large indentations in the snow on either side of the trail unmistakably marking a fall. At one point I saw a fellow biker get pulled into a berm. I heard an explicative and then, seemingly in slow motion, the rider just disappeared down &lt;i&gt;into&lt;/i&gt; the side of the trail. I rode up and complemented her on her “perfect 10,” and asked if she needed a hand. With a resigned look on her snow covered face she replied, “save yourself, man … save yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the challenge, I think a ride like this can tap into the child in us all. We try to avoid crashing, of course, but when we do inevitably have to dig our way out of a drift, it’s an instinctive reminder of the joy to be found in playing in the snow. I came to think of those indentations on the side of the trail as snow angels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another boost to the spirit this next section of trail provided was the opportunity to enjoy the awesome hospitality at the checkpoints. In particular, the folks at Flathorn Lake (mile 32) and 5 Star Tent (mile 46) were God-sends. A little warm stew and diverting conversation can do wonders for a beleaguered rider. The Flathorn crew had decorated their hut like a Hawaiian Luau complete with straw skirts and coconut bikini tops for the volunteers – worn over Carharts, of course. One of the volunteers was actually a friend of a friend and so we had some fun talking about our mutual acquaintance. To be honest, I can’t really remember many details about the conversation given my compromised, but improving, mental state. I was just grateful to have someone to keep me company while my glycogen stores recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The folks at 5 Star Tent were equally entertaining. Honestly, the whole experience there was a little bizarre. A ski plane crash landed near the tent earlier in the day and a snowmobiler recently came through looking for emergency services having broken her arm in an accident. Thankfully neither the pilot nor the snowmobiler had life-threatening injuries, but the unexpected activity of it all seemed to scatter the volunteers. There was a good deal of fuss over how to get the crock pot to heat up, if I recall, and someone else was struggling to blow up balloons. And all this was taking place right in the middle of the foggy, frozen Susitna River at dusk. It struck me again just how unique this journey was. The world outside was unquestionably bleak and yet these hearty volunteers were warm and joyous – sort of an Alaskan hallmark, I think. The only way to escape the persistent bite of the weather was to discover the delight in human relationships. And during my brief visits at the at the checkpoints in the middle of nowhere, these Alaskans graciously shared their secret with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Night fell, so did the temperature, and as the hours progressed all became quiet on the Susitna. The snowmobilers out preparing for the Iron Dog Race turned in and left the human-powered adventurers to carry on. Three or four other cyclists and I matched pace for awhile, following each other’s blinking tail lights, shouting encouragement here and there, and offering temperature readings and mileage stats as we pushed our way to the next checkpoint. The buzz on the trail was that EagleQuest Lodge was a little haven. It actually had a grill that stayed open all night, welcoming tired, hungry cyclists – and tempting them to throw in the towel. Given the slow pace, it seemed to take forever to go the 20 miles from 5 Star Tent, but I eventually rolled up to the lodge just after Midnight. There was a large group of people congregated at the turnoff, and I assumed they were the welcoming committee – but I didn’t get much of a welcome. I found out later that they were a news crew awaiting the arrival of the first runner, who was reportedly not all that far behind. That runner AGAIN! Was I ever going to shake that guy? He was like this constant check to my ego, continually taunting me. &lt;i&gt;Ride your own ride. Ride your own ride.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EagleQuest Lodge was all I could have hoped for and more. There was a bonfire outside surrounded by volunteers who helped me off my bike and oriented me to the cushy amenities the place had to offer. There was, indeed, an open grill inside, a drying rack for wet gear, and several cabins available to take a nap in – which sounded risky. There were also a lot of bikes around. I had finally caught up to some of the pack!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dragged myself into the lodge, hung up my gear, and sat down with some tired, ragged looking riders (I’m sure I fit right in), and ordered a breakfast sandwich and hot chocolate. A little protein, a little sugar, and I’d be good to go … or not. Just a few bites and my stomach began to protest! One of the keys to successfully getting through an endurance event is having a well-developed “junk gut.” The more calories you can shove in without having it all come back up the better. Apparently my junk gut wasn’t quite as honed as I had hoped and this sandwich was doing me wrong. I let it sit on the plate as I assessed just how severe my reaction was going to be. I must have sat there for quite awhile because I remember being jerked back to awareness when someone from across the room asked me if I needed help finding some motivation to finish my sandwich. I smiled sheepishly then decided to cut my losses with the lodge and get moving. As soon as I got up I knew something was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vision started to darken and my ears began to ring – I was going to pass out. I stumbled through the dining room, trying to stay conscious, and somehow made it into the restroom. Looking into the mirror, my face was completely white and a cold sweat had broken out on my forehead. I splashed some water on my face and took a few deep breaths, trying to calm down. The last time I had passed out was during a blood drive in college; struggling to maintain consciousness is not normally something I have to worry about. This ride was proving to me, yet again, just how much I had underestimated it. Fortunately, after a long conversation with myself in the mirror, I regained my composure and decided to find a comfortable spot to rest my head while the nausea passed – there was no way I could go back out there in my current state. I had heard there was a quiet room with a heated floor nearby. Sounded perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I entered the room I was met with quite a sight – about a dozen or so other riders sprawled out on the floor sound asleep. Apparently I wasn’t the only one in need of a reboot. I found a spare couple of feet on the floor, wedged myself in, and had a few blissful moments soaking up the heat radiating from below. I allowed myself some time to drift in and out of sleep, unsure as to how I was going to eventually pull myself away from the Siren song of EagleQuest and journey back into the frozen night. Yeah, Matt was out there somewhere, and if he had to wait for me at the finish line, well, he could deal. I needed a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I got up. I don’t know how, but I managed to shake the fainting spell and nausea. As much as I loved that heated floor, I needed to put that sandwich and the misery it caused as far behind me as I could. I refilled my water bottles with hot water from the restroom tap, crawled back onto my bike and got a hearty send-off from the volunteers outside around the fire. EagleQuest was at mile 63 which meant I had 37 miles to go and two checkpoints along the way – one at mile 80 and the second at mile 90. I could do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt surprisingly good to leave EagleQuest behind. The break was much needed (the sandwich, not so much) but my journey was not complete. In the spirit of promoting good morale by celebrating every little victory, I congratulated myself for resisting the pull of an early finish line. But once again I was out in the cold, forced to move forward or freeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail took on an eerie feel in these early morning hours, weaving its way between open lakes and dense forest. An icy fog formed over areas near the lake shores, obscuring the way ahead.  I was forced to keep my eyes on the few feet just ahead of me, looking for tire tracks and trail markers. Riders do take wrong turns out here. In fact, back at EagleQuest there was talk of a couple who managed to go ten miles in the wrong direction – that’s a solid two hours of riding – and then have to double back. There is nothing more discouraging to an exhausted rider than realizing they have been putting in unnecessary miles. Fortunately, I had managed to keep to the right path so far, but my new challenge was holding my eyes open so I would stay on it. I have never been a fan of rides that encourage sleep deprivation, and adding a three hour time change from Arkansas to Alaska compounded the issue somewhat, I think. Repetitive pedaling over an absolutely flat lake can have a sedating effect. At one point I had to get off my bike and jump up and down in order to wake up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in the ride, the finish line couldn’t come quickly enough. I had seen the Alaskan wilderness in all its glory, and it had put me in my place. The Susitna 100 had humbled me many times over. It was time to simply get this thing done. Other than warm broth and inviting smiles, The Cow Lake (mile 80) and Big Hunter (mile 90) checkpoints seem to blur a bit in my memory, but I will never forget the last ten miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after leaving Big Hunter for my final push I came upon none other than the runner. With a strand of blinking, multicolor Christmas lights running down the tether to his sled, he was hard to miss. Unlike our time together during the first part of the race, there was no playful banter. Instead, just a wave and a “good job.” I could tell the distance was wearing on him. And why not, after virtually four consecutive marathons … in freezing Alaska? After the race I learned that “the runner” was none other than David Johnston, the record-holder for the ITI 350 foot race category. His exploits are legendary. It was an honor to share same trail for a time. I did pass him, though. There was &lt;i&gt;no way&lt;/i&gt; this guy was going to beat me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I rode the final few miles of the loop back to Happy Trails Kennel, it struck me just how much of an emotional journey this had been. Sure, riding 100 miles through the bitter cold was a respectable physical feat, but I don’t believe I had ever crammed so much mental processing into one 24-hour period. My brain actually felt more exhausted than my body. What started as a mere prelude to a larger event became the event in itself, and that change was painful and all-consuming. I often find myself preaching about the value to be found in enjoying the present moment, indeed, this blog is based on a Shunryu Suzuki quote to that effect. Learning to live in the now can bring a certain peace and perspective that cannot be found while fixating on the future. Never, though, had I been through an experience that so clearly drove home the point. Were I to have remained focused on the ITI, I’m not sure that I would have been able to make it through the Susitna 100. Choosing to “be here now” is not merely a choice about whether or not to be happy in life – it is a choice about whether or not to actually live. If you’re not careful, the hypotheticals of the future can get in the way of what is truly in front of you, stoping you dead. The ITI could wait. I had a race to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt was waiting for me as I rolled into Happy Trails – over 22 hours after leaving it. I’ll never forget the look on his face. He said “congratulations,” but the nonverbal subtext was, “Jeez man, you were out there a long time. Sure you’re okay?” I asked him how long he had been waiting and he replied under his breath, “a while.” It turns out he had been there for six hours. The man is a beast! I parked my bike, shuffled into the Kennel, grabbed some cold nachos and a warm Coke, and none other than Marin Buser, the Iditarod champion himself, walked up to congratulate me. And, you know, I felt like I deserved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Matt and I packed up and prepared to go our separate ways, we talked about plans for our next mountain climb. Matt suggested, and I think brilliantly, that we use John Muir’s &lt;i&gt;Travels in Alaska&lt;/i&gt; to plot a course up Glenora Peak in British Columbia, retracing Muir’s steps during his adventure in the 1880’s. Apparently Muir took a minister along with him on the journey. Unfortunately, though, that minister ended up dislocating both of his arms during the climb, foiling Muir’s plans to reach the summit. We decided that our bid would be more a redemption story rather than a reenactment – and we decided we wouldn’t let another ten years pass before we made good on the plan!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a final twist to this story – sort of a cosmic joke of which I am, unfortunately, the butt. As I disassembled my bike I realized that in my anxious pre-ride fog I had managed to mis-thread my chain through my rear derailleur, causing it to rub significantly. In fact, I discovered that the part of the derailleur the chain had been rubbing on for the &lt;i&gt;entire 100 miles&lt;/i&gt; was almost sawed through. All you bike people out there reading this … just think about that for a minute. Yeah, I unnecessarily added God-only-knows how much extra resistance to my ride. I guess the constant sound of the tires on the snow and the heavy load on my bike kept me from realizing the mechanical ball and chain I was unwittingly dragging along. Alas, I will not blame the difficulty of the ride on my error – but I would like to take on that runner again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/gp/61920043@N05/76H5Pd&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 13:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/03/11/rolling-on-the-river.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/03/11/rolling-on-the-river.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>adventures</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Susitna 100 Live Track</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 175px; height: auto; &quot; src=&quot;/assets/su100bib.jpg&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; hspace=&quot;10px&quot; /&gt;Join my buddy Matthew Beedle and me for our ride in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://susitna100.com&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Susitna 100&lt;/a&gt;! A live track of our ride will be displayed below beginning at 9:00 a.m. Alaska Standard Time on February 17, 2018 (that’s 12 p.m. for my Arkansas friends). Matt and I passed the mandatory gear check last night. We had to have our survival essentials inspected by the race crew: -20 sleeping bag, bivy sack, foam sleeping pad, headlamp, flashing light, 64oz water carry capacity, and 3000-6000 calories of food. Our bikes are assembled and ready to go! Read more about our gear &lt;a href=&quot;/routes/adventures/gear/2018/01/27/susitna-100-gear.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Susitna 100 runs along the famed Iditarod trail in Alaska, beginning near Big Lake (about an hour and half north of Anchorage) and loops for 100 miles through remote woods and over frozen lakes and rivers – all covered in a blanket of snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And somehow (probably by virtue of my last name) I was able to get assigned bib #1. Auspicious, eh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=17b4f5a86ec8e425d1&amp;amp;hoursPast=0&amp;amp;showAll=yes&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://spotwalla.com/tripViewer.php?id=17b4f5a86ec8e425d1&amp;amp;hoursPast=0&amp;amp;showAll=yes&quot;&gt;See full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 08:26:53 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/routes/2018/02/16/susitna-100-track.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/routes/2018/02/16/susitna-100-track.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>routes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chocolate and Ashes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s a little strange that Ash Wednesday and Valentine’s Day share the same day, which doesn’t happen very often. It’s not quite as strange as Easter and April Fool’s Day coming on the same day this year. But that’s a problem for a later sermon. Today we stick with what Hallmark and the church give us -  a mash up of chocolate and ashes, love and mortality. Picture pastel candy hearts that normally say things like “Be mine” sporting a more Lenten message, like “Ashes to ashes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this day even more strange for our household, my valentine is traveling to Alaska today. He’s about to enter two winter races on his fat bike - that’s a bicycle with extra wide tires that you can ride over snow. These events will prepare him for his ultimate future goal of riding the 1,000-mile Iditarod race from Anchorage to Nome. The classic dogsled course opens up to bikers and snowshoers every February. To compete, each athlete must be self-sufficient, bringing all the gear and food they need for a winter adventure. I might add that in order to win my support for this undertaking, I was assured that no wolves or bears will be participating in the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been watching the winter olympics to get into the spirit of this upcoming adventure. I am always so moved by the remarkable human achievements of the athletes. I admit I get a little teary watching people win, or lose, or overcome whatever hardships they have faced to get to the games at all. The coverage capitalizes on this, of course. Maybe I’m not the only one who has gotten a little choked up by an athlete’s personal story or even a Toyota commercial this year. We teased Jason that we would make one of those slightly emotionally manipulative back story videos about him. Picture a ten-year-old picking himself back up after a bicycle crash in the schoolyard, with a busted bike but an undaunted spirit to pursue his dream, as told with piano music and the strange colors of old home movies. And then we would fast forward to footage of him riding solo in the quiet snow, with Dinali in the background, determined to cross the finish line with the trail still stretching out endlessly before him. I’m no expert, but I’m pretty sure that video would be good enough for prime time on NBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, whether or not that’s true, the picture of that ride in my imagination seems like a fitting image for this day day of both love and ashes. Valentine’s Day is about the passions that drive us, especially toward the objects of our affection, but also about our loves in general - the forces that lead one, say, to a love of winter endurance sports. Ash Wednesday, on the other hand, is the day when we lay those passions bare, and bring them to light for examination. Those things that drive us can sometimes lead us astray and get us off course. In the language of St. Augustine, what drives us can get misdirected or pointed in the wrong direction. We then find ourselves in sin, in all of its glorious variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The observance of Ash Wednesday invites us to strip away the distractions of our lives in order to reflect on this. Like a cyclist on a quiet, snowy trail, without a hotel or entourage or the fanfare of the start line, this day of fasting and prayer offers us insights that can only be gleaned away from the daily distractions of our lives. It’s not easy being without those distractions, but it’s good for the soul from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The church, in its ancient wisdom, understood this. For centuries, the church has commended this day for prayer, for fasting, and especially for penitence for all the ways we get off course. And Jesus had some advice about this. He was clear that as we do these practices, we shouldn’t do them for show, or for credit, or sympathy. On this day we are to get a blessed break from being concerned about the reaction or judgment of others. We should do these practices with an interior focus, because to do so is simply good for the soul. Our souls need to be freed from daily distractions and from the scrutiny of others from time to time. This helps us to reconnect with God, and to realign our passions once again with all that is good and holy in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The church also commends the receiving of ashes in the sign of the cross on our foreheads. This is a reminder that one day our passions will cease, our race will be finished. And the view from that finish line is a gift. It’s an invitation to sharpen our focus, like a solo athlete on the trail, letting distractions fall away to concentrate on what’s true, here and now. Ashes remind us of the training that our hearts sometimes need while we’re still on the course - a yearly crash course in penitence and honesty for a more faithful race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us will not go riding our bikes in the wintery Alaskan wilderness. But in a recent interview, one of the event’s superstars, Jay Petervary, offered some words of wisdom for all of us. “Embrace the journey,” he said. “Live in the moment… Know you have everything you need. Slow down and think about the ‘work’ you need to do. Do your ‘work.’ You can do more than you think you can.” That’s decent advice for Ash Wednesday. The church invites us to slow down on this day, and think about the work we need to do on our own hearts. The letter to the Hebrews has very similar advice, just a bit older than Petervary’s. It goes like this: “Let us lay aside every weight and the sin that clings so closely, and let us run with perseverance the race that is set before us.” (Hebrews 12:1). On this day of love and ashes, let us be reminded that we have everything we need, and we can do more, even love more, than we think we can in the race that is set before us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;[My awesome wife just preached this sermon today and it seemed to fit nicely on this blog. Plus, I feature prominently in it, so …]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 11:26:53 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/02/14/kate-ash-wednesday.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/02/14/kate-ash-wednesday.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>adventures</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Susitna 100 Gear Roundup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 200px; height: auto; &quot; src=&quot;/assets/fatbike.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; hspace=&quot;10px&quot; /&gt;I can’t say that riding my fatbike 100 miles through Alaska’s frozen wilderness is something I had always dreamed of doing. I mean, until a couple of years ago I didn’t even know that was something you &lt;i&gt;could&lt;/i&gt;. do. The larger question, I suppose, is why the idea of doing it crept into my psyche and took up permanent residence. It’s cold in Alaska – the temperatures in February can get down into the double-digit negatives. The riding conditions can vary wildly, from solid ice to slushy snow melt to fluffy powder. The gear is expensive and cumbersome – one studded tire for a fat bike costs over $200! So, what’s the deal? Is extreme winter fat biking fun or is it folly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of deciding to sign up for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://susitna100.com&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Susitna 100&lt;/a&gt; was not unlike deciding to take on the Appalachian Trail or the Tour Divide. At first the idea seems preposterous, not something any sane person with a career and family would do. “Stuff like that is for the crazies.” But then, slowly, surprisingly, strangely, the idea turns from being preposterous to a possibility. What would it be like to challenge my body and mind in that way … to go as far as I can and then go a little farther? What would it be like to experience the highs and lows of human emotion in such a dramatic environment? What would it be like to encounter others and share the joys and fears of the journey? How does undertaking something like this change a person? How would it change me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something “Shackelton-esque” about these adventures, I think. Fundamentally, they are opportunities to explore. I know that riding across a well-mapped portion of the tundra is not the same as attempting to map the way across Antarctica. Yet, it is still exploration – but more of the internal sort. Physical exploration seems to facilitate exploration of the self. The inner and outer journeys compliment and enhance one another. The farther I push myself down the trail, the farther I go internally and discover hidden resources I never imagined. True, there are many self-realized individuals who don’t camp in -20 degree weather, but I guess some of us need to experience the  extremes to learn our life lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophical justifications aside, this is really supposed to be a gear post. Some fellow bikepackers asked me to describe the unique equipment that winter fatbiking involves. Let’s get to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that most bikepackers would agree that their choice of gear-laden, wilderness riding over say, jogging around the neighborhood, is more than an alternative way of getting fit. Bikepacking is really a hobby. It’s an investment – kind of like brewing beer or building a DIY Heath Kit. Believe it or not, I can find just about as much joy puzzling out the way to load a bike properly as I can riding down the trail!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;center&gt;On the bike.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Tires and Rims.&lt;/strong&gt; The debate about rim and tire width is passionate. I’ve read numerous apologies on the benefits of one particular size combination or another. For example, some say that a 4” tire on a 100mm rim is just right, while a 5” tire on that same rim can bog things down a bit in particular snow conditions. Others say that despite the added weight of that extra inch, the fattest combo is always best. I get the impression that the actual ride differences end up being subtle. I already have “hundies” (100mm rims) on my Surly Ice Cream Truck, so I’m going with 5” tires to compliment them. I honestly don’t know if fatter is better – but it’s definitely cooler. The winter-specific change I did make was to swap out my Surly Bud and Lou tires for studded 45Nrth Dillinger 5’s. Studs don’t really do much for you unless you run into icy conditions, but I might as well be prepared. A good portion of the Susitna 100 route is along the frozen Susitna river. Also, I’ve decided to run these things with tubes. I figure a tubeless set up would be near impossible to fix in freezing weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Pogies.&lt;/strong&gt; These genius inventions are essentially permanent gloves, not only for your hands, but also for your handlebar grips, shifters, and brake levers. They go by lots of different names depending on the brand. Continuing with the 45Nrth theme, I bought a couple “Cobrafists,” and, man, they are excellent. I’ve ridden in single digit temps a few times this winter and my bare hands were toasty warm inside. You can even stash a few candy bars in the pogies to defrost them before eating. One thing to note, I did run into an install issue. I’m using a Jones Loop H-Bar instead of a regular straight handlebar and it took some trial and error to size the grips in order to fit the pogies where they needed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Brakes.&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I know DOT 5 fluid is not supposed to freeze, unlike mineral oil, but I did swap out my Sram hydraulic brakes for some trusty, mechanical BB7s. A friend at the bike shop (who notoriously hates BB7s!) had a spare set in his junk box so I took him up on his generous offer to donate them to the cause. I had some trouble with my Sram hydros anyway, and like my rationale for choosing to go with tubes in my tires, I figure having equipment I can maintenance in the field is wise. Plus, I’ve ridden with BB7s on my Salsa Fargo for lots of miles and have had great results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Sleep System.&lt;/strong&gt; In the off-chance that riders will have to bivouac out in the cold, three pieces of required gear for the Susitna 100 have to do with the sleep system. Each rider must have a sleeping bag rated to at least -20 degrees, a closed-cell foam pad (no inflatables), and a bivy sack or tent. My system consists of a -40 rated Marmot Cwm, a Ridgerest, and an OR Helium Bivy. The challenge is to organize them in such a way that set-up and take-down are as efficient as possible, as unpack/pack time can get cold fast. After a few iterations, I’m pretty pleased with the system I’m going to use. I put my sleeping bag, pad, and bivy sack together in a ready-to-use configuration (bag and pad inside of bivy), rolled it all up, cinched it tight with a velcro strap, and slid it all into a 55-liter dry bag. It is not the most compact solution, but it fits nicely on my rear rack strapped down with Surly Junk Straps. If I need to camp I should be able to unstrap, unroll, and crawl inside in just a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Water.&lt;/strong&gt; There are a couple of solutions out there for carrying water in below freezing conditions. The growing trend is to use a bladder and hose as one would while mountain biking in more temperate weather, however, they now make winter-specific versions that include a insulated hose to prevent freezing. I hear mixed reviews. The key to success, as with most of this equipment, is experimentation. Does one carry the bladder as a backpack under an outer layer? Does the hose snake up through the outer layer and emerge at the collar? Ask different riders and you’ll get different answers. In general, I prefer to use water bottles whenever possible. Fewer parts to worry about, and they’re carried on the bike rather than the body. I have Salsa Anything Cages mounted on both sides of my fork. Each will hold an OR Water Bottle Parka containing a 32-ounce Nalgene. I can easily slide a bottle out for a drink, but I do have to stop riding first – one drawback to this system. Also, a Water Bottle Parka containing a Nalgene is pretty easy to throw into a sleeping bag in order to keep it from freezing during an overnight bivouac. Regarding purification, filtering obviously won’t work in below freezing conditions, so melting and boiling snow is how it’s done. To compliment my trusty MSR WhisperLite stove I have a stainless 2-quart MSR pot – the same one I used on the Appalachian Trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;center&gt;On the body.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Boots.&lt;/strong&gt; Winter cycling boots have come a long way in recent years. The pioneers of this sport used flat pedals and Sorels, and some riders still do. The new method is to wear specialty boots with a clipless system. Again, the company that dominates the market is 45Nrth. A pair of Wolfgars are expensive but pretty much bomb proof. They’re rated down to -25 and have a removable liner for faster drying. I’ve done a few long rides in mine and have been pleased. Not only are they comfortable for cycling, but they’re also sturdy for hike-a-bikes through powder or over ice. You can even put studs into the Vibram soles for extra traction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Clothing.&lt;/strong&gt; This category has probably been the trickiest to dial in. As with other outdoor high-energy activities, the guiding principle is to regulate body heat by adding or subtracting layers. You don’t want to wear too much because sweat can freeze, which can lead to hypothermia, and you don’t want to wear too little because, well, that can lead to hypothermia too. It’s a balancing act. Here’s what I came up with. The base layer for my torso will be a close fitting, long sleeve, wool shirt. Next I’ll wear a mid-weight wool jersey. A fleece pullover will go on top of that, and a water/wind resistant soft-shell will serve as an outer layer. The fleece layer is the one most likely to come on and off. On my legs I’ll wear padded bike shorts underneath cold-weather bike tights. And I have a soft-shell outer layer for my legs as well. Socks are wool. For headgear, I have a wool hat that I can fit under a 45Nrth Lung Cookie. I will also pack my puffy down coat and some heavy duty gloves. I’ve heard that cycling with a down coat is generally a bad idea because the excess sweat can sneak up on you, but it’s a necessity for extended stops. Last but not least, I’ll be wearing a beard to give ice crystals a place to form – ‘cause that’s what all rugged Alaskans do, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;center&gt;In the belly.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-cog&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Food.&lt;/strong&gt;Getting it right in this department is one of those experience things. I have some, but could always use more. These days I tend to literally count the calories I’m packing and make choices based on numbers rather than how I think I’ll be feeling. I may not think I can, or would want to down four Pop Tarts, four candy bars, a bag of chips, and a box of Velveeta Shells and Cheese in a day, but I know that doing so will give me roughly 3000, easily digestible calories. I’ll likely burn more than that in a day, but it’s difficult to equalize your intake-to-burn ratio. There is only so much your stomach can handle while maintaining high output on the bike. For a century ride such as this, with no overnight likely, I will probably eat between 2000 and 2500 calories while riding. Were I to spend the night I would fire up the stove and cook my Shells and Cheese for a 1000 calorie recharge while sleeping. The required gear list for the Susitna 100 specifies that a rider must have at least 3000 calories in reserve (an extra day’s worth of food) before they are cleared through the final checkpoint (mile 77). So, I’m planning on taking around 6000 with me but only consuming about half of that. If someone else can come up with a more efficient way of doing this please let me know! &lt;i&gt;[If you want to know more of my thoughts on food, &lt;a href=&quot;/gear/2017/08/23/camping-food.html&quot;&gt;check out this post.&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll close with a couple of great quotes. The first is from fellow bikepacker, &lt;a href=&quot;http://jilloutside.com&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Jill Homer&lt;/a&gt;, who has been on some incredible winter adventures, including the 1000-mile Iditarod Trial Invitational. She wrote a book, &lt;u&gt;Into the North Wind&lt;/u&gt;, chronicling that journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;While shopping at an outdoor retailer in Anchorage, I came across a brochure for a hundred-mile bike race on the Iditarod Trail, the Susitna 100. I had no experience with endurance sports and no idea that riding bikes on snow was even a thing, but I was captivated. I signed up for the event, trained through my first dark winter in Alaska, and finished the grueling slog in twenty-five hours — soaking wet, dehydrated, depleted, and exhausted. Everything about the experience should have been a deterrent. Winter endurance cycling is one of those activities that looks fun from a distance, but in practice, actually it is not — similar to heavy drinking. And yet, similar to heavy drinking it continues to draw people back, almost against their will. Is winter cycling an addiction? I’m inclined to say no, and yet I can’t deny that I was hooked.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the second is a recruitment notice to become a crew member on the Endurance, Earnest Shackelton’s ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Men wanted for hazardous journey. Small wages. Bitter cold. Long months of complete darkness. Constant danger. Safe return doubtful. Honour and recognition in case of success. &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m proud to join the ranks of the “crazies.” We’ll see if that attitude holds when February 17 comes around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/susitna-100_192324?scaleControl=false&amp;amp;miniMap=false&amp;amp;scrollWheelZoom=false&amp;amp;zoomControl=true&amp;amp;allowEdit=false&amp;amp;moreControl=true&amp;amp;searchControl=null&amp;amp;tilelayersControl=null&amp;amp;embedControl=null&amp;amp;datalayersControl=true&amp;amp;onLoadPanel=undefined&amp;amp;captionBar=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/susitna-100_192324&quot;&gt;See full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 11:26:53 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/gear/2018/01/27/susitna-100-gear.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/gear/2018/01/27/susitna-100-gear.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>gear</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Epic Connector</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since I heard about the Womble Trail I wanted to ride it. Those familiar with the world of mountain biking know that the Womble is a legendary IMBA Epic route, considered to be “immersive, technically and physically challenging, beautiful to behold and worthy of celebration.” It’s a 33-mile stretch of almost uninterrupted singletrack that traverses the southern part of the Ouachita National Forest. A friend of mine once suggested that the creator of the Womble must have been a genius. Despite the nearly 6000 feet of climbing, a rider is able to stay on the bike and keep pace for virtually the entire length of the trail. It’s an expertly graded, smooth, “flowy” ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is basically in my backyard, I had no excuse but to plan a trip. The Ouachita Trail, which was recently given IMBA Epic status as well, connects to the Womble at its northern terminus. That gave me an idea. Why not connect the two into one multi-day bikepacking adventure? I would start at the southern terminus of the Womble, south of Mount Ida, Arkansas, and end at the Lake Sylvia Recreation Area about 40 minutes outside of Little Rock. The route would span 102 miles, climb nearly 15,000 feet, and take three days to complete. And on November 30, 2017 I put the plan into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate drove me out to the Womble trailhead and wished me luck. I promised to send her the custom message on my GPS SPOT tracker each evening after finding camp, as is our custom. I think the message is still the same one from my Divide ride: “Made it! No bears, no crashes, love you!” And so far that message has always proven to be true (well, maybe I’ve had a crash or two but nothing crazy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hit the trail a little after 2 p.m. and enjoyed an afternoon of smooth riding. The stories are true. The Womble is EPIC. It’s just as flowy as they say. However, I quickly learned that it’s not without its dangerous sections. Much of the Womble’s footprint is about a foot in width and cut into the side of steeply graded slopes. So, on one side of the trail there is a slope up and on the other side, an often sheer drop-off into the abyss. If you take your eyes off of the trail to chase a noise in the woods, for example, you’re likely to drift right off the edge. I speak from experience – I slid probably 20 feet before stopping myself. And I wish I could say that I learned my lesson after that, but it took a couple more freaky falls before really committing my eyes to the trail in front of me. These slopes should be of particular concern to bikepackers, with all that cumbersome gear gumming up the bike’s handling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 15 miles I found an acceptable ad-hoc campsite a little ways off the trail. Since the sun sets so early this time of year I didn’t want to ride much past 5 p.m. Ramen was tasty. Mood was up. Slept well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning I set out around 7 a.m., found a water source and filled up. Having learned my lesson from the day before, I managed to avoid falling into the abyss and was able to savor the genius of the Womble. Miles 23 and 26 were particularly scenic, as the trail follows a high, narrow ridge that overlooks a remote section of the Ouachita River. Despite the exhilarating  riding and the inspiring views, it was about this point that I realized my food stores were a little low. For whatever reason I often underestimate the energy I’ll be burning on these trips and pack fewer calories than I should. At home in the kitchen, with a full belly, I tend to think more about saving weight than cramming extra calories into my bag. I had been hoping to find somewhere to buy a few candy bars along the way, but no luck. The Womble, Epic trail that it is, insists on staying hidden in the woods, away from the hustle and bustle of civilized life and its conveniences. Normally this is a good thing, but not when you’re hungry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My growing calorie deficit eventually turned from a concern in the back of my mind to a reality. Around mile 32 my mood took a nose dive (remember: “food is mood”). The sky was overcast, the temperature was dropping, the sun was on its way down, and I had only done slightly more than half of the mileage I had hoped for that day. Ugh. And to complicate matters I took a wrong turn. There’s nothing more frustrating than putting in extra miles going in the wrong direction, especially when you’re racing a against the sun. In hindsight, this is when my nicely planned bikepacking trip turned into an adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style of the trail changed dramatically all of a sudden. Instead of that genius flowy stuff that was the trademark of the Womble, the trail got so seep and rocky that I had to hike my bike. I searched my memory for where I could have taken a wrong turn but the white blazes that mark the Womble were still clearly coming – so I just kept on climbing. Eventually I came to the top of a ridge and found a perpendicular trail marked with blue blazes. Confused, I pulled out my phone hoping for service so I could consult Google Maps (My usually trusty GPS had an incomplete basemap and didn’t show enough detail for me to get my bearings). Luckily, I did get service and after some head scratching I realized that I had reached the Ouachita Trail – just several miles before I had expected to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the Ouachita Trail is marked with blue blazes and its side trails are marked with white blazes. One of the OT’s side trails hit the Womble – also marked with white blazes – and I had mistaken the “Big Round Top Mountain” side trail for the Womble. Once I figured this out, my calorie starved and overly panicked brain calmed down and I knew what I had to do. I could just ride NE on the OT, eventually run into the actual OT/Womble intersection, and continue on my journey. And 3 miles later that’s exactly what happened. Although I found my way again, it turns out that the adventure had just begun. As I bid goodbye to the Womble and started down the Ouachita Trail I learned my next lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite sharing IMBA Epic status, the Womble and the OT are nothing alike. Where I could typically maintain an overall average of 5 mph on the Womble, I found I could hardly manage 3 mph on the OT. It is simply made for hiking rather than mountain biking – and so I did a lot of hiking. By the time I hit mile 40 (25 on the day) I was done. It was only 4:30 p.m., but my physical reserves were gone and so was my motivation. I found a spot to camp on the side of the trail, built up a fire, ate my ration of Anne’s Mac and Cheese, and hoped for a good sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning I took my time getting ready, slowly packing up my gear, needing a burst of positive emotional energy to lighten my ride a bit. My sleep, although good, didn’t completely reset me like I wished it would. I was daunted by the prospect of a full day on the OT, fighting both the hills and a calorie deficit. To top it off, I was a little lonely. Yeah, it had only been a day, but I hadn’t seen anyone else on the trail. And then I felt a little selfish and irresponsible. Kate was at home packing up the kids for school by herself while I was out here “recreating,” and feeling sorry for myself. Ugh. I knew from experience, though, that these unproductive thoughts were par for the course. The “demons” often crawl out of their hiding places on these trips, itching for battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still honing my fighting skills, but I’ve learned a few war tactics over the years. The “phone a friend” option always helps if cell service is available. Some external motivation goes a long way. If that fails, firing up the GPS and SPOT tracker gives me a lift. I imagine a GPS device casting invisible tethers out into space where those tethers are then tied to others that reach back to civilization. Even if the connection isn’t two-way, at least I know one exists. Probably the most powerful way to combat the demons, though, is to keep putting one foot in front of the other. The closer you get to your destination the more muffled their war cries become. It’s not a quick fix like a phone call can be, but it’s ultimately the most effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ouachita Trail passes through some gorgeous country, always keeping things interesting. The mountains in the southern Ouachita National Forest are grand by Arkansas standards. At mile 66 I summited Ouachita Pinnacle at an elevation of 1973 ft, the highest point on this trek. And after enjoying the specular view, I got to enjoy the dizzying descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick with mountain biking down switchbacks is to become skilled at shifting your weight uphill at the turns, unclipping your uphill foot for counter balance, and applying your rear break while going at just the right speed. Once you nail this maneuver you can count on a nice “drift” on the turns allowing you to stay on your bike throughout the descent. At least that’s what you shoot for. In reality, I probably successfully did this about half of the time, and only maybe a quarter of the time made it look pretty. In addition to the challenge of switchbacks, the OT offers a number of blowdowns for the biker to navigate. I had my share of humbling spills trying to hop the logs. Again, a bike with the additional weight of bikepacking bags can throw off one’s sense of what is possible. I eventually learned that if the success of a hop looks marginal then I should be cautious and get off the bike to climb over it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the day came to a close I realized I wasn’t going to make it to Highway 7 as I had hoped, so I decided to shoot for Big Bear Shelter instead. It’s one of the many Appalachian Trail style shelters on the OT, each generally spaced seven miles apart and near water sources. Big Bear is situated at the base of a steep bluff with a stream flowing just 30 ft away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I pulled into the shelter area memories of the Appalachian Trail came flooding back. The “lean-to” style is distinctive, with one of its four sides open allowing room for several hikers at once to toss in sleeping bags and crash after a long day. Also, like shelters on the AT, Big Bear has a logbook where hikers can share their thoughts on the day’s travels, offering tips about water sources and sharing some uplifting words for the weary. I spent a few minutes browsing through its dirty, tattered pages reading about the adventurous souls who had begun their journey back in Oklahoma, at the beginning of the OT, and were just a few days from completing their trek. As an exhausted biker, it was a gift to feel the “hikers high” come through those pages. When you’ve had time to beat back the distracting demons a bit, like these OT thru-hikers had, a real appreciation for the present can develop. Honest joy can be found in the simple things, like a good night’s sleep, the warmth of the sun, or, as I found next to the logbook, a extra pack of ramen noodles a fellow traveler had left behind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That evening, as I watched the bright moon rise above the Bear Creek bluff, I sat by the fire and indulged in a Cherry Pie Lära Bar and TWO packs of ramen noodles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the third night behind me and a little over 30 miles to go, 20 of which would be on the easier Lake Sylvia area dirt roads, I set out in good spirits. The final 10 miles of the OT proved to be its typical, extremely challenging yet beautiful self but ended with a smooth several miles of downhill all the way to Highway 7. It kind of makes me wonder if the IMBA officials who gave the OT its Epic status only rode that section!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lake Sylvia portion of my ride, which I had traveled many times, was like coming home. I know those roads intimately and was able to relax while riding, no longer having to worry about a narrow trail with precipitous drop-offs. And at 2 p.m., exactly 72 hours and 102 miles from when I began, I arrived at the Lake Sylvia parking lot. A sunny spot near a Ouachita Trail trailhead invited me over, and I gladly accepted, melting off of my bike and collapsing onto the ground to await my pick-up. I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can now say that I’ve seen with my own eyes the hidden spot in the middle of the Ouachita National Forest where the Ouachita Trail and the Womble intersect – it no longer only exists on my topo map!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fab fa-flickr&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flic.kr/s/aHskqFkHNM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/3ovttcau5xj83e5/wt%2Bot%2Bsl.GPX?dl=0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Download the GPX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;This route is 102 miles end to end and climbs and descends 15,000 feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/the-connector_188628?scaleControl=false&amp;amp;miniMap=false&amp;amp;scrollWheelZoom=false&amp;amp;zoomControl=true&amp;amp;allowEdit=false&amp;amp;moreControl=true&amp;amp;searchControl=null&amp;amp;tilelayersControl=null&amp;amp;embedControl=null&amp;amp;datalayersControl=true&amp;amp;onLoadPanel=undefined&amp;amp;captionBar=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/the-connector_188628&quot;&gt;See full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 11:26:53 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/01/11/the-connector.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://buddha.bike/adventures/2018/01/11/the-connector.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>adventures</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
